{
  "reference_number": "11409",
  "clauses": [
    {
      "question": "1. What process should the Government use to set a new emissions reduction target in legislation?",
      "question_index": 0,
      "answer": "The Government sets a 2050 target in legislation now",
      "answer_index": 0,
      "notes": "I have no idea whether the current government is qualified to do so, and someone could quit the Climate Change Commission at\n\n anytime, and be replaced by anyone else. All I know is we must follow the long-term maths, and be willing to sacrifice, if necessary for\n the long-term good."
    },
    {
      "question": "2. If the Government sets a 2050 target now, which is the best target for New Zealand?",
      "question_index": 1,
      "answer": "Net Zero Emissions - Net zero emissions across all greenhouse gases by 2050",
      "answer_index": 1,
      "notes": null
    },
    {
      "question": "3. How should New Zealand meet its targets?",
      "question_index": 2,
      "answer": "Domestic emissions reductions only (including from new forest planting)",
      "answer_index": 7,
      "notes": "The average person is not qualified to answer this; I know I'm not. I just know that safeguards regarding credits are never certain. Do\n what's possible here first, including efficiency and energy-use reduction to start, then mitigation later."
    },
    {
      "question": "4. Should the Zero Carbon Bill allow the 2050 target to be revised if circumstances change?",
      "question_index": 3,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": "Yes, but only by a panel of scientific experts, not a government. See the US or past NZ governments if you want examples of\n changing environmental policy for nefarious purposes."
    },
    {
      "question": "5. The Government proposes that three emissions budgets of five years each (i.e. covering the next 15 years) be in place at any given time. Do you agree with this proposal?",
      "question_index": 15,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": "You really need to read page 36 to understand this. Whatever makes this plan accountable, with measurements... I'm for it."
    },
    {
      "question": "6. Should the Government be able to alter the last emissions budget (i.e. furthest into the future)?",
      "question_index": 4,
      "answer": "No - emissions budgets should not be able to be changed",
      "answer_index": 9,
      "notes": "Only make stronger, not weaker. It sounds like you're trying to build something into this bill that will destroy it long term, or let National\n come in and knock it down later, and say they're doing it for the economy."
    },
    {
      "question": "7. Should the Government have the ability to review and adjust the second emissions budget within a specific range under exceptional circumstances? See p36 Our Climate Your Say",
      "question_index": 5,
      "answer": "No",
      "answer_index": 8,
      "notes": "Only make stronger, not weaker. It sounds like you're trying to build something into this bill that will destroy it long term, or let National\ncome in and knock it down later, and say they're doing it for the economy."
    },
    {
      "question": "8. Do you agree with the considerations we propose that the Government and the Climate Change Commission take into account when advising on and setting budgets? See p44 Our Climate Your Say",
      "question_index": 6,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": "Environment is the foundation of all the other bullet points, thus the later bullet points can not and must not outweigh the first."
    },
    {
      "question": "9. Should the Zero Carbon Bill require Governments to set out plans within a certain timeframe to achieve the emissions budgets?",
      "question_index": 7,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": null
    },
    {
      "question": "10. What are the most important issues for the Government to consider in setting plans to meet budgets? For example, who do we need to work with, what else needs to be considered?",
      "question_index": 8,
      "answer": null,
      "answer_index": 5,
      "notes": "Build bridges to the new economy, and do not be a slave to the technology or ideology that got us into this mess in the first place.\n\nBoldly act, even in ways difficult to explain to the public."
    },
    {
      "question": "11. The Government has proposed that the Climate Change Commission advises on and monitors New Zealand's progress towards its goals. Do you agree with these functions? See p42 Our Climate Your Say",
      "question_index": 9,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": "And make their recommendations public. Publish them widely, whether they agree with Government actions or not."
    },
    {
      "question": "12. What role do you think the Climate Change Commission should have in relation to the New Zealand Emissions Trading Scheme (NZ ETS)?",
      "question_index": 10,
      "answer": null,
      "answer_index": 5,
      "notes": "I have no idea."
    },
    {
      "question": "13. The Government has proposed that Climate Change Commissioners need to have a range of essential and desirable expertise. Do you agree with the proposed expertise? See p45 Our Climate Your Say",
      "question_index": 11,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": null
    },
    {
      "question": "14. Do you think the Zero Carbon Bill should cover adapting to climate change?",
      "question_index": 12,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": "Adaptation, unfortunately, will be the primary role of government when it comes to climate change. We are only 4+ million people, +\ncows & sheep emissions. We must do our part, but it will not be enough to prevent our world from looking totally different."
    },
    {
      "question": "15. The Government has proposed a number of new functions to help us adapt to climate change. Do you agree with the proposed functions? See p47 Our Climate Your Say",
      "question_index": 13,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": "Also, put away money now, billions a year, to help fund future mitigation we will need. This generation and previous ones caused it;\n\nwe must pay for it."
    },
    {
      "question": "16. Should we explore setting up a targeted adaptation reporting power that could see some organisations share information on their exposure to climate change risks?",
      "question_index": 14,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": null
    },
    {
      "question": "Do you have any other comments you'd like to make?",
      "question_index": 16,
      "answer": null,
      "answer_index": 5,
      "notes": "Now is the time to be brave. Make a stand against those who only care about present day, their quarterly profits, and/or don't have\nthe knowledge or audacity to make necessary change. Show how you're different. Let's do this.\n\n\n\n\n You have elected to withhold your personal details from publication."
    }
  ]
}
